<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on abowtiekindofguy</title>
    <link>https://www.akshatjha.xyz/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on abowtiekindofguy</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:33:47 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.akshatjha.xyz/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>On Reservation</title>
      <link>https://www.akshatjha.xyz/posts/thoughts-on-iit/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:33:47 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.akshatjha.xyz/posts/thoughts-on-iit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I used to hate the idea of engineering. In fact, I was almost going to do a BS (Research) at IISc. Almost &amp;hellip;, until 12th September.&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.akshatjha.xyz/images/iisc_admission_withdrawal.png&#34;&#xA;    alt=&#34;IISc Admission Withdrawal&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;p&gt;IISc Admission Withdrawal&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The thing is that on 11th September, IIT Bombay released the results for JEE Advanced 2022. I was ranked 264 in the country and 24 among the Economically Weaker Section (&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Economically_Weaker_Section&#34;&gt;EWS reservation&lt;/a&gt;) aspirants.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I came across the quota for the Economically Weaker Section almost by accident in Class 12, a few months before JEE Main. The idea seemed quite appealing. If you earned below 8 lakhs and did not own a residential property exceeding 1,000 square feet (and some limit on agricultural property as well), you would be eligible to gain access to the reserved EWS seats for admissions to public schools, such as IITs. We (my parents and I) lived in a relatively calm and semi-posh gated society in Ghaziabad, which we were only able to afford because of another house my father had built more than a decade ago in Vikas Nagar in Delhi (which appreciated in value greatly) and a generous loan from the Indiabulls Housing Loan Corporation. This cozy home measures 915 sq. ft. and was the only asset we owned at the time. The COVID-19 pandemic had left us surviving on loan moratoriums and help from friends. And I would be lying if I said I was putting 100% of my efforts into college admissions. After countless rounds to the Ghaziabad Tehsil Office and around 15K in bribes later, we had an EWS certificate. I am fairly certain I could have one made, even without satisfying the necessary conditions (although perhaps with a larger bribe).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hello World</title>
      <link>https://www.akshatjha.xyz/posts/hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 16:46:01 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.akshatjha.xyz/posts/hello-world/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Just checking if everything is working.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
